Finding Aid for Frederick C. O'Dell papers 1918-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frederick C. O'Dell Papers 1918-1919
O'Dell, Frederick C. (Frederick Charles)
1 oversize photograph
0.2 linear feet
59 architectural drawings
185 maps
Master engineer of 1st Battalion, 310th U.S. Army Engineers, in charge of the Army Topographical Office in Archangel, Russia during the Allied intervention in Russia, 1918-1920, the "Polar Bear Expedition." Collection includes maps, architectural drawings, photographs, and miscellanea relating to the work of the 310th Engineers in Russia. Architectural drawings include plans for buildings and fortifications.
93830;Aa;2;UAl (photographs and papers)
M;7063;.A7;1918;O3 (maps and drawings)
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Frederick C. O'Dell (donor no. 8900 ); a portion of the collection was transferred from the William L. Clements Library (donor 1333 ).
The collection is open for research.
Frederick C. O'Dell, Master Engineer, 1st Battalion, 310th Engineers, U.S. Army, was in charge of the Army Topographical Office in Archangel, Russia, during the American Expedition to North Russia, 1918-1919.
The collection relates entirely to O'Dell's experience serving with the American Expeditionary Force, North Russia, 1918-1919. The bulk of the collection consists of maps and architectural designs for buildings and fortifications constructed by the American Expeditionary Force, North Russia. Most of the maps and designs were produced by the 310th Engineers. In addition, there are two folders of photographs taken of the area and a scattering of miscellaneous official documents.
Subjects:
O'Dell, Frederick C. (Frederick Charles); Polar Bear Expedition.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Arkhangel'sk (Russia); Barracks--American--Russia (Federation)--Arkhangel'sk (Russia); Fort Custer (Mich.); Forts and fortifications--Russia (Federation); Military art and science.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Soldiers--American--Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; United States. Army. Engineer Regiment, 310th.
Subjects: Maps
Archangel'sk (Russia)--Maps.; Polar Bear Expedition--Maps.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920--Maps.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Campaigns--Maps.; United States. Army. Engineer Regiment, 310th.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.
- Photographs and Miscellaneous Papers
  - Photographic views of Archangel and photos of barracks, stables, fortifications, and other structures built by the 310th Engineers, 31 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographic views of Archangel and photos of barracks, stables, fortifications, and other structures built by the 310th Engineers, 4 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Documents relating to assignments and memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Group portrait of 310th Engineers while in training at Camp Custer, Michigan (Folder 4)
    In UAl oversize
- Maps
  The Maps series includes general maps of the Archangel district at scales ranging from 1:420,000 to 1:20,000, large scale maps of cities and towns involved in military operations, reconnaissance and road maps, and maps of fortifications and military positions during the 1918-1919 campaign. Maps issued by the Allied Mapping Section and the Mapping Section, Dvina Force are noted in the contents list.
  - Map of Archangel district, Russia. 10 verst series. Allied Mapping Section, 1919, 6 sheets; Scale ca. 1:420,000 (Folder 5)
    See description in folder 17
  - Archangel district, Russia. 1 verst series. Allied Mapping Section, 1919, 79 sheets; Scale 1:42,000
    Each sheet contains two squares, corresponding to the squares marked on the 10 verst sheets in folder 5. See description in folder 17
    - Archangel city and Onega areas (Folder 6)
    - Pinega area (Folder 7)
    - Lower Dvina River, Emtsa River, and Archangel-Vologda Railroad areas. (Folder 8)
    - Upper Dvina River and Vaga River areas. (Folder 9)
  - Map of Archangel district, Map No. 1. 8 verst series., 1918, Scale ca. 1:336,000 (Folder 10)
    (9 sheets of a 22 (or more) sheet map. Have sheet nos. 2,4,5,7,10,11,14,19,22). See description in folder 17.)
  - Spetsial'nyi plan" chasti Arkhangel'skoi gubernii. 5 verst series. 1919, 4 sheets; Scale 1:210,000 (Folder 10)
    (In Russian) See description in folder 17.
  - Map of Archangel district. 10 verst series., October 12, 1918-November 21, 1918, 4 sheets; Scale 1:420,000 (Folder 11)
  - Territory from Lyavalya to Konetsbor, south of Dvina River, undated, 8 sheets (of a 10 sheet map ?; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 11)
  - Plan: district of Economy, September 14, 1918 (Folder 12)
    (no scale shown)
  - Soundings over sandbar: Vaga River Ust Vaga, June 6, 1919, Scale 1:1200 (Folder 12)
  - Map of Pechora River system 1919, Scale 1:1,260,000 (Folder 12)
    (See description in folder 17)
  - Map of Archangel and Solombola, October 27, 1918, Scale ca. 1:13,440 (Folder 12)
  - [untitled Led and Tarnya Rivers area, undated] Mapping Section, Dvina Force., Scale 1:42,000 (Folder 12)
  - North winter trail, Archangel-Pinega, preliminary sketch of emergency trail (reindeer) February 13, 1919, Scale ca. 1:440,000 (Folder 12)
  - Map of Morjegorskaya district, undated, Scale 1:84,000 (Folder 12)
  - Plan showing districts in the vicinity of the towns of Emetskoe, Siiskoe and Vaimuga, January 29, 1919, Scale 1:42,000 (Folder 12)
  - Road traverse, Shredmakrenga-Tarasevo January 27, 1919, Scale ca. 1:42,000 (Folder 12)
  - Defensive Maps
    The Defensive Maps series consists of blueprint maps created by the 310th Engineers in North Russia. They were originally wired together in a folder marked Appendix No.4, Section 3. They have been left in O'Dell's original order. Items numbered 6A, 37A, and 64A were not on O'Dell's list. Item 61 on O'Dell's list was not found. The original introduction found in the folder has been placed in Folder 17.
    - Sketch showing location of fortified areas undated, 1. (Folder 13)
    - Map of track from Smollney to Six Verst Saw Mill June 3, 1919, 2.; Scale 1:10,560 (Folder 13)
    - Map: Lyavlya vicinity March, 1919, 3.; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 13)
    - Rikasikha area, undated, 4.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 13)
    - Konetsbor area, undated, 5.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 13)
    - Fortifications at Verst 506, undated, 6.; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 13)
    - Plan of fortifications at Verst 490, 1919, 6A.; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 13)
    - Map of Malie Ozerki and vicinity, April 1, 1919, 7.; Scale ca. 1:3,600 (Folder 13)
    - Plan showing Bolshieozerki road defence, Verst Post 18, April 4, 1919, April 29, 1919, 8.; Scale ca. 1:5,280 (Folder 13)
    - Sketch: Selo Bolshie Ozerka undated, 9.; Scale ca. 1:40,000 (Folder 13)
    - Sketch map showing winter and summer roads Obozerskaya- Bolshoi Ozerke, undated, 10.; Scale 1:105,600 (Folder 13)
    - Section of Obozerskaya- Chekueva road from 7th verst west of Malieozerkie to 10th verst, March 29, 1919, 11.; Scale ca. 1:10,800 (Folder 13)
    - Sketch showing Oberskaya district from Verst 470 to Verst 476, December 4, 1918, 12.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 13)
    - Verst 466, Archangel-Vologda railroad, undated, 13. (Folder 13)
    - Position at 466, undated, 14.; Scale ca. 1:31,680 (Folder 13)
    - Proposed fire lanes and new blockhouses V-458, undated, 15. (Folder 13)
    - Sketch of block house defense showing lines of fire and track sidings between Verst 454 and Verst 455, November 27, 1918, 16.; Scale ca. 1:3,600 (Folder 13)
    - Position at 448 and blockhouses between 447- 448, undated, 17.; Scale ca. 1:2,640 (Folder 13)
    - Positions at 445 and 446, undated, 18.; Scale ca. 1:2,640 (Folder 13)
    - Verst 446 to 444, November 28, 1918, 19.; Scale ca. 1:3,600 (Folder 13)
    - Sketch showing positions near Verst 445, January 23, 1918, 20.; Scale ca. 1:2,640 (Folder 13)
    - Rough map shewing disposition of Emtsa station and line of trenches at V.P. 443 December 1, 1918. G.H.Q. Intelligence, 21. (Folder 13)
    - Map of Plesetskaya, Russia, 1918, 22.; Scale ca. 1:420 (Folder 13)
      (Copied from original dated 1913)
    - Map of Onega, Archangel district, Russia, January 9, 1919, 23.; Scale ca. 1:10,500 (Folder 13)
    - Bolshie-Ozerki-Chekuevo-Turchasovo roads, etc. undated, 24. (Folder 13)
    - Chunovo, undated, 25.; Scale ca. 1:5,250 (Folder 13)
    - Chekuevo defenses, December 15, 1918, 26.; Scale 1:8,462 (Folder 13)
    - Cheshiuga, February 12, 1919, 27.; Scale ca. 1:5,250 (Folder 13)
    - Filyava undated, 28. (Folder 13)
    - Kavkula., March 20, 1919, 29.; Scale ca. 1:5.250 (Folder 13)
    - Kueshova undated, 30. (Folder 13)
    - Kleshevo, February 18, 1919, 31.; Scale ca. 1:5,280 or 1:5,250 (Folder 13)
    - Road map: Kleschevo to Telza R., January 26, 1919, 32.; Scale ca. 1:42,000 (Folder 14)
    - Kialovanga, February 19, 1919, 33.; Scale ca. 1:5,250 (Folder 14)
    - Turchasovo, showing positions held during offensive on, December 30, 1918, February 17, 1919, 34.; Scale 1:8,400 (Folder 14)
    - Sketch of operation on Turchasovo, undated, 35. (Folder 14)
    - Village of Seletskoe, December, 1918, 36.; Scale ca. 1:10,500 (Folder 14)
    - Kodish front [dated 28-18-18], 37.; Scale ca. 1:10,500 (Folder 14)
    - Defenses on road to Kadish, undated, 37A.; Scale ca. 1:2,400 (Folder 14)
    - Kodish defences, undated, 38.; Scale ca. 1:2,400 (Folder 14)
    - Kodish defence map, April 8, 1919, 39.; Scale 1:5,000 (Folder 14)
    - Shred Makrenga and vicinity, April 1919, 40.; Scale 1:26,000 (Folder 14)
    - Kholmogori area, showing blockhouses, etc., undated, 41.; Scale ca. 1:42,000 (Folder 14)
    - Sketch of Emetskoe defenses, undated, 42.; Scale ca. 1:7 200 (Folder 14)
    - Morjegorskaya and defences, April 8, 1919, 2 sheets; 43-44.; Scale ca. 1:7,200) (Folder 14)
    - Ust Morje and defences, May 12, 1919, 45.; Scale ca. 1:3,600 (Folder 14)
    - Plesso and defences, May 19, 1919, 46.; Scale ca. 1:3,600 (Folder 14)
    - Usolia district and defences, May 13, 1919, 47.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Defence map of Bereznik, undated, 48.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Map of Bereznik and Osinovo defences, undated, 49.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Topsa area, December 18, 1918, 50.; Scale ca. 1:21,000 (Folder 14)
    - Shussuga and vicinity, with defences of Shussuga, May 9, 1919, 51.; Scale 1:5,000 (Folder 14)
    - Sushuga defense map, undated, 52.; Scale ca. 1:1,800 (Folder 14)
    - Toulgas district defences, undated, 53.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Rostaffskaia outpost sketch, undated, 54.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Kurgomen district defenses, January 4, 1919, 55.; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 14)
    - Outpost sketch of Kourgomen, undated, 56.; Scale 1:20,000 (Folder 14)
    - Map: Savoy Copse, Kurgomen area (west end) showing 60 pdr. gun pits, dugouts, mine dugouts, and galleries, June 4, 1919, 57.; Scale 1:900 (Folder 14)
    - Ust-Vaga defence map, undated, 58.; Scale 1:10,000 (Folder 14)
    - Artillery map Kitsa area, undated. Mapping Section Dvina Force, 59.; Scale 1 :42 000 (Folder 14)
    - Kitsa- Vistavka district defences, April 17, 1919, 60.; Scale ca. 1:10,500 (Folder 14)
    - [missing], 61. (Folder 14)
    - Fort. plat of Kitsa, undated, 62. (Folder 14)
    - Fort. plat Yevstevskaya, undated, 63. (Folder 14)
    - Sketch of Schenkursk undated, 64.; Scale 1:2,400 (Folder 14)
    - Denislavia from sketch undated, 64A.; Scale ca. 1:7,200 (Folder 14)
- Designs
  The Architectural Design series consists of plans and designs of buildings and fortifications constructed by the 310th Engineers in North Russia. They were originally wired together in a folder marked Appendix No. 4, Section 2. They have been arranged by work number. The Original introduction found in the folder has been placed in Folder 17)
  - Barracks for 104 men September 17, 1918, 6 sheets; 4 (Folder 15)
  - Standard latrine [date obscured], 5. (Folder 15)
  - Officers' quarters September 26, 1918, 6 sheets; 8. (Folder 15)
  - Standard bath house October 8, 1918, 11. (Folder 15)
  - Standard brick stove October 14, 1918, 12. (Folder 15)
  - Standard 8-man blockhouse October 7, 1918, 13. (Folder 15)
  - Standard 20 man blockhouse October 17, 1918, 15. (Folder 15)
  - U.S. Engineer drafting office November 11, 1918, 18. (Folder 15)
  - Block plan of Michigan barracks showing sewer and water lines November 29, 1918, 20. (Folder 15)
  - U.S. Army stores warehouse built at Bakaritza, Russia, October 9, 1918, 3 sheets; 21. (Folder 15)
  - Incinerating plant for Michigan barracks November 12, 1918, 31. (Folder 15)
  - Wireless station November 20, 1918, 32. (Folder 15)
  - Sergeant's mess, 30 men capacity Obozerskaya, Russia, January 14, 1919, 34. (Folder 15)
  - Stable for 60 horses at Obozerskaya, Russia, January 15, 1919, 35. (Folder 15)
  - Officer's quarters, 10 rooms at Obozerskaya, January 15, 1919, 36. (Folder 15)
  - D.A.D.O.S. log warehouse at Obozerskaya, Russia, January 18, 1919, 38. (Folder 15)
  - 30 yard winter range for British machine gun school January 24, 1919, 41. (Folder 15)
  - Proposed bridge Verst 422, January 25, 1919, 43. (Folder 16)
  - Blockhouse at Verst 581, February 18, 1919, 45. (Folder 16)
  - Blockhouse at Michka, Russia, February 20, 1919, 46. (Folder 16)
  - Barricades around lumber blockhouses at Verst 445, February 24, 1919, 48. (Folder 16)
  - Dvina Force blockhouse February 25, 1919, 54. (Folder 16)
  - 50 man dugout for reserve platoon at Verst 445, March 6, 1919, 55. (Folder 16)
  - Shell proof shelter for Kurgomen district March 18, 1919, 56. (Folder 16)
  - Machine gun emplacement March 8, 1919, 58. (Folder 16)
  - Proposed splinter proof shelters for Kurgoman district, April 1, 1919, 2 sheets; 62. (Folder 16)
  - Type of blockhouse erected for defence of Rostovskoe, Dvina Front, April 1, 1919, 63. (Folder 16)
  - Officer's R.A.F. house boat May 2, 1919, 2 sheets; 64. (Folder 16)
  - Men's R.A.F. house boat May 7, 1919, 2 sheets; 65. (Folder 16)
  - Shelter and foundation for 6" howitzer March 8, 1919, 69. (Folder 16)
  - Bridge Verst 458, March 10, 1919, 70. (Folder 16)
  - Standard latrine for Morjegorskaya, June 2, 1919, 72. (Folder 16)
  - Sketch for barrel raft as used in Kurgomen area, May 17, 1919, 73. (Folder 16)
  - Sketch for refrigerator (built in existing barn) Kurgomen area, undated, 74. (Folder 16)
  - Sketch for flash screen as built for 60 pdr. guns, in Kurgomen area, May 16, 1919, 75. (Folder 16)
  - Sketch for splinter proof 60 pdr. gun pits as built in Kurgomen area, May 18, 1919, 77. (Folder 16)
  - [Untitled Fortification at Shenkursk?, undated], 3 sheets; 79. (Folder 16)
  - Dug-out May 28, 1919, 80. (Folder 16)
  - [title obscured. Bridge] April-May 1919, 81. (Folder 16)
  - Dvina Hospital ward room May 15, 1919, 82. (Folder 16)
  - Section of fire trench and A frame Kurgomen, May 30, 1919, 85. (Folder 16)
  - Artillery observation post, Kurgoman district (St. Pauls village) June 2, 1919, 86. (Folder 16)
  - Drawing of dugout for M.G. Co. April 30, 1919, 87. (Folder 16)
- Map descriptions
  - Map descriptions (Folder 17)